hello and welcome back to voicecraft a
medium for artful and experimental
conversations
that seek to share insight into the
nature of psyche
culture and our relationship to an
evolving world at the turn of an age
it's part of a broader culture-making
vision to build wiser pathways to
connection and collaboration
and more effective protocols for sense
making and generative
meaningful and healthy interaction there
are breadcrumbs to follow
if you look
this is the kind of conversation i've
been working probably like five years to
have
you know um which is an awful lot of
effort to put in for some friends that
you haven't met
but um thank you much appreciate it
so look i mean i see these um recordings
i'm starting to see them it's like a
bit of a weird mixture of of um
kind of like a friendship sort of joy
but then also a sort of serious
ceremonial element
because we could just be having this
conversation not recorded and so
you know it leads me to consider well
what's the purpose of this it's not like
there's
not very much content on the internet so
there's quite a bit of it
and so to what degree can we create
something beautiful and helpful
in a way that speaks not only to the
imminence of what's between us here but
that actually
serves as a some sort of beneficial and
helpful artifact
so in that sense it's um very much an
ongoing experimental
process with the context of a podcast
itself but also with
um obviously this being recorded with
video as well and um
how this fits into a broader life
project
of fundamentally extending the kind of
invitations for people to participate
in we can say broadly processes of
meaning making and
sense-making in ways that aren't as
as perhaps we've grown to engage
in them
these days so you know between us
there's like a great interest in young
and um i suppose
with the slightly more esoteric
um and a cultural slant on things this
is something i've had
something of an interest in but take
myself to be sort of you know an
interested student in these kind of
matters
although with respect to young i've i've
read
somewhat more and i feel its influence
on my way of making sense to be
significant in many regards and the
other thing as well is that
i see these as opportunities to to
really see if we can
essentially further our understanding
together in the way of synergy
you know so we can think about that from
an alchemical lens or
just a straightforward synergetic lens
we can see what comes of our whole of
perception if we manage to
share and really hear in a way that
furthers what it is we can't sense about
the world and um
crystallize it into so
you know it's probably um helpful in
particular to the people
listening and not viewing to place
names to voices and perhaps just to get
like
very brief like just a couple minute
introductions but let's not do this
in in a boring way um i can say a little
bit i can say that
um eric you're someone who i came across
in the world of jung online
some amount of years ago now i've lost
count since i've been in curfew the last
10 weeks and i can't really relate to
even what happened six months ago
some amount of years ago and um
podcasts like individuationing becoming
myths that make us
you're a writer and a podcaster and
you've been working on a book
recently and you're also a coach someone
who
who i see is on some kind of mission to
understand the psyche um and and to
present
um to people ways guides
of working with their own psyches and
each other so that they can live
healthier more meaningful lives this is
a beautiful mission
um and anderson you're someone who you
just gave us a tour of your room before
there's
um imposing bookshelves on all sides you
are
you are a wizard in a library someone
who teaches
young and cognitive scientists cognitive
science at the university of toronto a
dnd master
both of you have been on the podcast
before it's bloody nice to have you here
so as some sort of introductory question
eric i'm curious
what sort of um what what drives you to
even show up to a conversation like this
what's what's the
if there's a some sort of magic or
energy you feel
well sort of catalyzes your interest and
fundamentally like why are you
why are you here at all um i'm going to
choose to see that as a lens of why am i
here on the podcast as opposed to why i
am embodied and
doing the life thing and the reason i'm
really excited about this podcast is
uh i it's very rare for me to be in the
presence of people who
understand deaf psychology and
you know cognitive psychology and
evolutionary psychology in a way that
can challenge the conclusions that i've
come to so that i can
further my understanding because much of
my
learning about jungian ideas is
alone and you know alone is an
interesting thing to really think about
if you really understand what jung is
saying
but um i'm really excited to offer
what i believe and then to have it be
challenged and reconstructed
and um to hear how you two see it as
well so i can
allow that to you know fall into the
soil and i can
do some new things and i'm excited to
see what arises
yeah beautiful same to you anderson what
your buddy here for mate
i liked being here last time a lot and
also
uh no i did really thoroughly enjoy it
last time um
i guess similarly i mean you know we
were talking about this a bit at the
outset
and you know i have i have
a sort of a boundless interest in in
young in a lot of things
but but young has occupied so much of my
attention
um and yet despite the fact that i've
read his work many times there are still
passages that are um
if not quite opaque in a state of sort
of ongoing unfolding revelation
you know things that i get more out of
and
you know similarly you know operating as
kind of an auto didact and reading this
stuff on your own i feel is like
kind of a time-honored tradition almost
in this sort of work
but at the same time there's a you know
like jung says right there's a kind of
chemical reaction
that happens between people um
consciously and unconsciously
and you know i think any opportunity to
talk to
smart interesting people about things
that strike me as being
really important and and essential to
what it means to be human and
and what's going on in general um is
always a treat
uh you know i um often have the
opportunity to talk about this stuff but
of course you know i'm very often
teaching it so it's it's me
giving my interpretations and it's not
that there isn't back and forth but
again it's uh
it's just a really cool opportunity to
talk to to people that are sort of deep
deep enthusiasts and and and are working
with it
right instead of just sort of
overviewing it so
so yeah so i'm looking forward to the
chemical reactions i guess is what i
mean
yeah something to pick up on immediately
that's coming to me
from both of what you're saying there is
um
this relationship between understanding
and working with
jungian ideas with depth psychology more
broadly
and then doing it in isolation versus
doing it with others
um which speaks to so if we if we take
an understanding that the psyche is some
sort of
relationship a dynamic relationship
between
parts that are in some kind of
evolving growth like
solar system like relationship i've
heard you describe it kind of anderson
at least with respect to the archetype
of the self
that we have this dynamic relationship
of parts and um
how how to how to relate to that in the
actual
social context because when we show up
in group situations
it's often the case that someone's got
this kind of vibe someone's got that
kind of vibe
what is it like to recognize ourselves
in others
and is there a way of actually optimally
coming into relationship with each other
where we can come to learn more about
ourselves
and each other so yeah it strikes me as
something that's quite resonant to
this sort of podcast and project as well
because what we do see more broadly in
society i think
is a breakdown of effective ways to come
together as
communities the socio technology of
being together
along with the psycho technology of how
we relate to our
inner sort of worlds so i think that's
for me why
one of the reasons why this is such a um
you know why i'm so enthusiastic about
seeing what can come
of um of these kinds of conversations
yeah absolutely yeah so
so eric i know that um you
are a coach working with aubry marcus
and various places and i've i know the
the project is sort of called
fit first service um please correct me
if i'm wrong about any of that
and there's a sense in which there
you're working with large groups of
people
in a sort of semi you know even though
it's for a short period of time a semi
sort of tribal like
setting where it's about getting people
into a kind of right relationship
of becoming with each other i'm just
wondering
the degree to which your sort of
understanding
of um jung even has come through in
those kind of environments
100 so um the context of fit for service
is it's a year-long program and we
create a new
curriculum each year and the curriculum
this year is the hero's journey
and so we're using um the 12 stages of
the hero's journey
as is understood by joseph campbell
which most people
don't know but i'm sure both of you know
you know the roots of that came from
young
and i don't know if he specifically
called it the hero's journey but the way
that i understand it is
it seems to be the archetypical story of
how the psyche goes through
transformations
and we're trying to like what's really
interesting
is and again one of my favorite reasons
um
why i love to coach is when you're
transmitting an idea to somebody
their body will tell you instantly
whether or not what you are saying is
resonating with them
and so it's this constant tuning that
you don't get if you're just thinking
alone
and it's been really fun to try to
tell people the hero's journey in a way
where it resonates with them but what i
am finding as a coach that
just i love it is that people will tell
me they don't know
what to do i will then tell them a
brief summary of the 12 stages of the
hero's journey
and just by describing the ordinary
world
and describing the call to adventure and
describing the refusal of the call
and describing crossing the threshold
every single time people are like oh i
know what the thing is
and like it's it seems to be evidence of
an archetype
and to your point um some of the
research that i've been doing for the
book with aubry about
uh community is that if people
self-report as feeling lonely
they're more likely to die early than
people who are obese
than people who live in an area with
high air pollution
than people who smoke a pack a day or
what's the last one but anyways it has
the highest correlation to all-cause
mortality early death than any
known factor that we are aware of right
now and
it's something like one in four people
report not even having a single close
friend
and the thing that i have found about
what
creates the feeling of loneliness is if
it feels like you can't be
if if you feel that you aren't seen
by somebody and describing the hero's
journey
archetype or structure to people really
it's teaching them like these are the
steps that you have to go through
to be able to actually connect with
people because it connects you to
who you are authentically and then gives
you the courage to step out of the
quote-unquote ordinary world which is
the archetypical matrix
and then what i am finding is that
by giving people that framework and then
giving them the opportunity to connect
like the magic and the healing that is
happening
within the container is more powerful
than anything that the coaches
could consciously articulate or enact
am i allowed to ask questions i don't
want to uh i don't want to like
blow out the secret level on your
workshop
let's go okay okay so i'm curious
i'm curious because um
yeah uh so so you know the the idea of
the hero's journey right
is probably maybe got even more
popular penetration maybe than like jung
himself right
so it's one of those things that i mean
it's been it's been dominating hollywood
uh since star wars and because of star
wars
um but you know it has it has lots of
currency like it's a pretty standard
thing that
um here in canada anyway they teach it
in english classes right in high school
it's one of these like lenses
that you you often use um
[Music]
when you when you work with people with
it and i'm thinking about this from sort
of a therapeutic lens and i think that
there's
a pretty strong family resemblance
between sort of therapeutic work and
coaching work
um when people go to work with
it what do they do
like how do they how do they code it
like do they work with it dramatically
or are they just like getting a sort of
a grasp of the stages and then
mapping life events in like do you find
that people differ
in ways that they yeah yeah so it for
sure
currently is b where they're just
getting the overview and then they're
mapping life events onto it
what i would love is to get to the point
where
i understand it well enough where i can
put them through dramas because i think
that that would be even more powerful to
help people and i think that that's
the psychological function of ritual
is to put people through dramas that
actually help them either embody
physically or body energetically new
modes of being
that will that they can then bring to
their ordinary life that can help them
you know
be heroic quote unquote um but yeah
currently
simply giving people that framework it's
like their psyche will begin to do
the work on its own to help them
see like oh this is the obstacle right
now
or oh this is the way through the
obstacle right now
or oh these are the people in my life or
the voices in my life that are keeping
me from
doing the thing that i feel called to
genuinely do
right um that's really cool
uh if you're looking at the dramatic
side i feel like i should be getting a
kick back from the dungeons and dragons
people at this point but
if you're looking at the dramatic side
there are a few
uh more finely developed tools for
putting people through a
structured dramatic narrative arc of
that kind than role-playing games
dnd per se may not be it because it's a
little bit of like a
kill and loot simulator at the end of
the day um
but but there are sort of beautiful uh
role-playing games out there you know in
for every genre and artistic dimension
you can think of
and some of them do um just sort of
astounding things when you put
uh this kind of archetypal framework on
you know
um i've used the hero's journey in
games a lot and i do a certain amount of
therapeutic gaming
in addition to right and before kovid
shoved the whole thing we were just
firing up a role-playing game study
about
uh tabletop rpgs and um autism spectrum
population
and one of the things we've really
looked at when we've in between that
work and working with students is
precisely that that like
giving the dramatic narrative space to
embody
heroism and and sort of doing a
proxy thing where you can if you're
subtle about it
symbolize issues in certain ways right
um so if you have a population that you
know has
somewhat shared issues there are things
that you can
code in a sense into the drama that
reflect or emulate so i'm
really really interested in that
yeah it's it's it's uh the thing is it's
shockingly effective and i don't know
why
i'm surprised because it's an extremely
participatory art form and i
i think it's running on the source code
of human
the consciousness organization principle
but um but nevertheless it's surprising
right
um when it does take there's there's
something really um
striking about it um okay i do have a
question
and and uh i'm interested to get your
your take because this is something i've
considered at lengths and
young has some things to say about but i
still consider it a bit of a mystery and
it's in this this vein
what do you think it is about
explicating for somebody
in in these kinds of terms that you're
talking about right
something that's structurally archetypal
for them that catalyzes that action
because we in a sense i mean you know if
we believe that these things are
archetypal and that they're sort of part
of the
foundation of the way our our minds our
psyches are organized right
right and we in a sense just do it
because we can do it not consciously
what do you think it is about
about laying it out in conscious terms
that that can gel or catalyze
action i mean obviously there's lots of
ideas in there potentially but i'm
curious you thought
so my intuition is um when
ever i see research or i study um
animals in captivity or animals that
have been domesticated
um they show a level
so like animals that are domesticated
show symptoms of neurosis and mental
illness that no wild animals show
and also um no wild animals show
evidence of ptsd but domestic
animals do show um symptoms of ptsd
and my intuition is that uh culture has
gotten to a point
where we live inside of boxes inside of
boxes inside of boxes looking at boxes
so
a city is a box that keeps out nature
and then we live inside of a house that
is a box that keeps out nature and then
we live inside of a room
that is a box that keeps out nature and
then we look through a screen which is a
box that keeps out nature
and it feels like uh there's so many
layers of cement of cultural
conditioning because one of the things
is like
the greatest storytellers in the culture
i think that's the most sacred like act
that a person can have in a tribe we
live in a culture where
the greatest storytellers are
corporations and they're not trying to
tell stories
that like the elders were trying to tell
around fires
and so i think we live in a population
where the majority of people
are essentially domestic domesticated
animals who don't even know what their
instincts feel like and that
articulating what seems to be
a story that represents like
the instinct to growth
it almost needs to be transmuted in
language to these creatures that are so
disconnected from their instincts that
the only thing that they've learned how
to really interact with is their mind
and language
that's interesting um
yeah uh this really plugs into the
i have something of a running critique
of of disney and
don't get me wrong i like disney movies
as much as anybody they're very
entertaining
um but i have a running critique of
disney about
how essentially speaking they you know
um
they've not just battlerized myths uh
and fairy tales
but they've sort of weaponized them uh
in in an important sense and they've
gotten
very good at doing this it's one of the
reasons that freaks me out a little bit
because
you know like i i alluded to with with
star wars
i have a i have a very strong opinion
about star wars i'm i'm a 70s child so
it's it's my religion in some ways my
childhood religion
um and uh uh
and of course star wars did something
really specific right which is
it explicitly took the hero's journey
and it applied it in a way that nobody
expected this movie about weird robots
and hairy monsters and laser swords to
become
an international cultural phenomenon
right um
the producers didn't expect that george
lucas didn't expect that the actors
didn't expect it right
um and yet it became this huge thing
basically because
it it applied this structure i do
sometimes worry
actually um this is my concern that
you know in the way that other kinds of
mythological representations and
cultures can be
um worn down right overdrawn
um that it's possible to come i mean you
know you're sort of pointing out right
the storyteller around the fire
um or at a certain time of year you know
it's like now is you know when the
pole star is at its highest and so this
is when we tell this story
um and instead what we have is like here
is a story that has this
recognizable emotional transference
thing when we run it for you
and now we're going to run it over and
over and over and over and over and over
and over and over
um so i worry about that stuff sometimes
i mean
myths can always slough that off
right and
emerge french but at the same time um
you know i sometimes do worry about the
idea that yeah the big storytelling
powers
um have really sort of turned or
attempted to turn myth into a crank
machine
for right you know yeah so anyway so
what i find is important and powerful is
when you only use language to transfer
the story
in the absence of making the person
um absorb the image that you're
providing
you allow their psyche to provide the
image in their imagination
and that is in a sense like a waking
dream and so it becomes personal
it can slouch off the concrete of the
corporatization of this myth
and so i find that if you
give it to people in person through
language alone
that their psyche is able to put the
flesh on the bones
as opposed to if you're watching a movie
the flesh is being provided for you by
the images and the
musical score behind it and um
i think that that is one of the ways
that the myth can stay alive and not be
prostituted by you know these entities
that are
their primary goal is to make money
yeah um something that comes to me also
is that
there are many myths you know and um
it's not clear to me that i've even
necessarily
um breed breathe them all
in and out to the same degree right and
this speaks to the point about how
movies might be co-opting
me or us in various ways by preventing
by presenting some
rather than others and almost treating
that sort of
relationship like just another box and
there's part of me that's always wanting
to push beyond the edge of that
and so it'd be a tragic thing for
example to have the
the hero's myth be something that just
enables people to sort of
get their stimulation and kicks to
essentially stay where they are and
fundamentally not end up participating
in the world
which makes me think of um the uh
i'm more fuller context of actual
participation and embodiment which is
more akin to what you're speaking about
in the context of the
various kind of coaching processes
you're talking about eric that's so
important
but i'm also interested in this
relationship between different kinds of
myths like as a
as a male i think i've been more
interested in
more typically male myths but i'm
also interested in
female myths of our time and then i'm
interested in
well what if we have to create new myths
right which is a which is a tough thing
to say when it comes to jung in some
respects because
there's a skepticism regarding the
degree to which
archetypes can be created at all rather
than just merely
re-particularized but i'd like to
presence this in relationship to
this other sort of complex concept which
is might be some sort of idea of
emergence
in nature and emergency in culture we
might say the technological
emergence we're experiencing at the
moment this creation of new channels of
communication
the ubiquity of information but how
difficult it is to process it and so
the various ways we're being hacked by
algorithms to present to us
what the algorithms will sort of uh
find you know think we're gonna find
most relevant so that we can continue to
just
do the consuming thing so it's like
to what degree um could even
the myths that have been so powerful for
us no longer serve us
i mean i know i've put like four or five
things into the fourth there so
please like just pick one or pick what
pops out to you at all from all of that
but
i have sort of three loosely connected
thoughts
um so
you know considering all that stuff i
sort of think in in i guess a few
different axes right so i think along
the line of time um and sort of into the
the future into the past but like the
line of time and beyond sort of our
immediate time
and i think about sort of scale um you
know scaling it up to whatever
uh extent and then and then and then i
think of it in terms of i guess
the the terminal versus the cyclical so
so in terms of like time well no
actually
let's let's do scale first in terms of
scale
you know i think about some of these
technologies of connection
you know facebook social media whatever
and
the evidence of course seems to be
mounting up that they're of course
cross-connecting us not just consciously
but uh unconsciously
um and it's the unconscious effects um
that that you begin to really see at
scale so
the way i've been thinking about it is
like when we built the internal
combustion engine
right what did we think we were getting
we thought we were getting personal
transport
personal transport and convenience
that's what we thought and we built
these machines and we put a billion of
them on the planet and we all thought we
were in the age of happy motoring
getting around
but at scale that's not what we built
what we built was a terraforming engine
to turn our planet into venus that's
what we actually built
a machine that pulls dinosaur wine out
of the ground and pumps it into the
atmosphere
and raises the temperature for everybody
right that's what we actually built
and it's only at the limited scale that
it looks like the age of happy motoring
right so when i think about technologies
and i think about this stuff
i i have speculated a bunch lately that
in a way
a lot of these cross-connecting
technologies initially
you know you think about the the 1990s
wired vision
utopian vision you know of what the
internet was going to be and it was
going to connect us together
and it did that until we got the pattern
recognition on the algorithms up to the
point when they began to be able to make
predictive
right predictive intrusions into right
and when we monetize the tension in this
very fine-grained way
right and then what has the impact of
that well what we think the impact is is
that people
get this feed of that they're
interested in right
just like like a goose with one of those
feeding tubes
um for foie gras but what they actually
got if you pull back from scale
is a machine that seems to be raising
the global emotional temperature
mostly by siloing people and then
feeding them
whatever outrage they happen to already
agree with it was a very tight
way right so so there's kind of a scope
and scale thing and i often wonder about
what that
means in a sense archetypally is there
some
is there like a hot house archetype here
that is maybe a new
thing in some sense right right and
maybe sort of emerging
in a new way that didn't quite exist
before because the
the the technology wasn't there so i
think about that
when i think about the timeline aspect
um
you know from that perspective it's it's
in some ways
i think clear that that jung at least in
late young
did intend for a certain amount of
historical evolution so if you look in
ion his book ion or i think a bit more
sharply in answer to job right
answer to job is a fascinating little
book right because it
it looks at the story of job so you know
the book of job in the bible
is uh you know this wager that takes
place between god and
and the devil when the devil was still
an employee and not an enemy
and they're both sort of sitting on the
cliff side and the devil's like
hey your servant job seems quite pious
and god's like yup and then uh he's like
i bet you if i absolutely destroy this
guy i can get him to renounce you
and god basically you know says you're
on uh
ten bucks for the winner kind of thing
and so they they then proceed right he
allows the adversary to do this and he
just crushes this guy's life right he
kills his children and robs him as far
all this stuff and then you get to this
final scene and in the final scene
you know god appears and job has of
course the temerity
to just for one instance sort of say
like you know
why does this have to happen anyway
basically right
god freaks out he freaks out this is old
testament god
you know full throated and you know he
says uh
you know where where where worse now
when i laid the foundations of the earth
can't thou drop leviathan with a hook
like he really he's like i'm god who are
you i'm god
and y'all's interpretation of that i
think is so
um interesting it's heretical but it's
interesting
which is that that event you know
looking at the
sort of the the two halves of the bible
right old testament to new testament
but that's the event that produces in a
sense in god
guilt god feels ashamed for what he's
done
now if we think about that in sort of
jungian terms as he was right then what
we're talking about is the self the
archetype of the self and its
relationship to the ego
in some deeply collective sense suddenly
undergoing a kind of moment of
consciousness which is supposed to be at
the whole heart
of what the encounter between the ego
and all the other architects is right we
lend them consciousness
that's why they all want our attention
that's why we matter
and so the self sort of has this moment
of consciousness where it stops being a
capricious tyrannical and feels
bad enough that in young's
interpretation that's what then
precipitates the incarnation
god has to then incarnate right so that
he can take on sufferings
so that he knows what's going on on the
ground like
and that's you know and obviously right
there's a million
theological and interpretive and
hermeneutic you know objections that you
can bring to this
but at the heart of it that's a really
interesting example for sort of the
hinge
that's in the bible right this
transition this transition between this
this angry plague tossing
smashing quite capricious sometimes
good-natured
being and this like god of love who we
see in uh right it's very greek
we see in the in the new testament in
christ's incarnation so
just right there young is really
pointing at something in an eye on
more broadly right and he's pointing at
these sort of transitions
that are occurring where the archetypes
can
seemingly you know in in a collective
sense
change change their stance change their
mode on more than
sort of merely cosmetic or or minor
right
and you know whatever we could argue all
day about how much
the interaction between architect and
culture but
yeah and then the third thing that
strikes me and this is something i think
about a lot
is which will kind of pitch out there i
guess
um so archetypes are cyclical
right that's in their nature um that
they that they follow a cycle it's that
thing that makes them somewhat
predictable they're sort of circular
things
um in the way that time used to be
circular for humans
right rather than linear so it was you
know the the cycle and the procession of
the equinoxes and all that
jazz right there was a circularity and
archetypes are very circular
um and so i wonder sometimes
what it means for the circularity of
archetypes and
how they help us predict things in our
lives that we might be coming up on
sort of a massive historical
discontinuity
that things might be actually really
changing like in a radical way
fairly soon and you know we can take our
pick i keep one toe in the like kurtz
violin
um transcend in a machine consciousness
pool but i'm thinking mostly here about
like
climate change right and the potential
that
in the same way as animals which are
essentially cyclical
can't change as the environmental
conditions change i sort of wonder what
it means
like whether our myths are going to have
to run a gauntlet because they won't be
predictive and of course we have myths
for that right phoenix and rebirth and
i don't know so that's
wow okay so so many things came up that
i want to touch on um i have a couple of
things that came up
when tim first asked the question but i
really want to explore
one thing for a moment it is a
revolutionary idea to me
to to really connect to the possibility
that could the ego react to the self in
such a way
that it fundamentally changes the way
the self is
you know guiding or orchestrating the
ego's life and that
maybe it requires a moment of
uh the ego contesting the self
that would precipitate that but it seems
to be
if you use the story of job as the map
here
that you know because most people at the
beginning of their
quote unquote transformational journey
they are fighting against the self but
it seems like it hasn't
earned through suffering the ability or
through
piousness and then suffering the the
space to
question the self in such a way that
would create guilt in the self
so that's a really interesting idea that
i'm going to think about a lot
is that can the ego get to the point
where it's earned the right to
potentially maybe critique the self in a
way that can transform the self that's
that's radical and very interesting to
me the
couple of things that came up when tim
first asked the question is
i imagine the psyche on one level as
like the ocean
and to try to keep it down through
anything is like trying to pour cement
on top of the ocean like good
luck
and um what i find in my community so
like
a lot of people that i know they do
things like ayahuasca
and mushrooms with intention and
inside of containers that have been
honed for thousands of years
and in the same way that dreams at times
like my intuition is that it it were
dreams and visionary states that produce
all myths
that have ever arisen into the space of
ever being able to be articulated
that that function is still alive in
every single human on this planet and we
are all watching
and we are all paying attention and all
all of our cells
inside of us capital s cells we're
watching what's going on
and people are having dreams and people
are having visionary experiences
and i believe that whatever archetype
needs to arise to increase the
adaptability
of the collective psyche it will come
and now
but do we have the ability to listen to
whoever the people are
and do we create containers for people
to even be able to hold that space and
be able to articulate those stories in a
way where we don't give them
pharmaceuticals that numb them and put
them inside of boxes you know like
do we even have the cultural container
to allow for people to be
profits you know like that's a really
interesting thing to feel into
um and i also do agree that
it feels like once the rise of the
internet happened that it connected
psyche in a way that was completely
unknown and has never been known before
and my intuition is like in the same way
that the
personal ego goes through its
transformation where like in
early teenage years that's when the
shadow becomes kind of the
like that's when it comes into full
force and the ego doesn't quite know how
to contend with it and there's the most
volatile behaviors that um
hopefully a integration can come in
early
20s or 30s and for people that have
midlife crises because they've ignored
it for 20 years then it comes up again
and my feeling is that on a collective
level we're like a 16 year old
like with the rising of the internet
within the last 30 years like we are
just beginning to truly contend with our
shadow
and right now it feels you know like how
a parent probably feels about their 18
year old who is just completely
rebelling
and there's just anger and destruction
everywhere
my intuition um and i skewed to optimism
is that there is going and we are in the
midst
of like that revolution in the
collective
psyche and that my hope
is that new myths will arise and they
will have platforms and they will able
to be heard and they will like there's
so many independent people
making independent art that you know i'm
hoping that there will be a star wars of
our time
that instead of being created by a
corporation is created by an independent
that
is so unique that completely resonates
with whatever
story needs to be heard right now that
will allow people to contend with
the issues that are arising
beautiful let me let me make one
meta sort of meta reflection on the
dynamics of the conversation so far
because
okay so we began with this conversation
i kind of
introduced you guys open the space we
shared some intentions we began talking
a bit of a flow starts to develop and
then i
in the last time i spoke i put like
oh this is uh this is a fire alarm here
i'm gonna
i'm gonna beat myself for you guys
so the uh jungian and so okay i've
labeled the part inside of me that has
completely downloaded the weirdness of
young and synchronicity and all that
thing and i call her evie
and like that part of me whatever you
were about
to say was interrupting whatever was
wanting to come out that it created a
synchronicity around you that kept
you from bringing forth that idea that's
that's the interesting
laugh that comes up out of me
well it's finished now
i can bring it back i can bring it back
and the point was really to
to actually to introduce a bit of chaos
right
so so i put about four ideas on the
table
and i can imagine the listening
experience for some people was kind of
like
whoa but then anderson was able to
take some of that raw material crafted
into some points which he might not have
mentioned
otherwise in that particular instance
and then now we reflect on that
and we continue speaking but i'm raising
this because there's a kind of um
this is part of the collective art
process and there's different roles to
play in the dynamics of
generativity and conversation itself so
if i was with
other people speaking i wouldn't have
said those kinds of things right
there's times when um i might have to be
the one providing a more steady flow of
coherence
but in this context because of who i'm
with i can play a certain role
that then enables the whole of the
conversation to become more
so for people listening and just because
this is sort of in resonance with the
broader scope of this
project and i think also what we're
speaking about in a very interesting way
an understanding of the dynamics of
communication and the different roles we
play in it i think is deeply part of
what we're
speaking about here if we can kind of
it's like different instrumentation
and if we can come to the right sort of
bass track if we
introduce the right instruments and then
maybe we can add one or two people
and then there's already the kind of um
the fellowship of players there we can
add one in and all of a sudden then
does that provide a context for
something radically new
to actually presence itself in a safe
way and then be caught
you know just like a moment of insight
it might just be to the void
might be back into the chaos but if
there's some people there who can pick
it up
and bring it on well then maybe that's
something um
something deeply worthwhile
um i find that
in these kinds of spaces and i mean you
know it's
it's obviously it's very sort of
conversational despite the
the you know relative focus but the ones
that i find most pleasing and maybe this
speaks
actually to what we're already talking
about with these cycles i love the ones
where there are like
two or three dozen untracked
insightful jewels that get fired out the
side and you'll ah we'll come back to
that
uh but then inexplicably you end up back
where you started without i once had a
conversation that started on the topic
of lobsters went for like three hours
and then ended on lobsters and it was so
beautiful and it was not like
it was not a move we just got there you
know in this spontaneous
um way um
and you know and spontaneity is a big
part of it um
i think it's important with something
like this that
you know that well i mean you know none
of us can feel too
guarded right there has to be that open
space
um probably helps i imagine we're all
quite high openness
um right so having that kind of thing uh
land makes a big difference
um yeah yeah
i was just thinking about about this
process and then also thinking about
this this business of sort of the ego
pushing
pushing back and um pushing back against
the self
and you know i think wrestling with god
or wrestling with angels is like that's
like an honest part of the work
right i don't think you can get too deep
into thinking about stuff without
having some serious beef with the the
creator
in the state of affairs like worse or i
think you're maybe not looking at it
deeply enough and then
part of that is sort of shadow work and
part of it is
realizing like the shadow goes all the
way up and all the way down right
that that god is not simply nice
um and that and that the universe is not
simply nice it's often nice
it's possible to make it nicer and you
can always appreciate things and so on
and so forth and there are meaningful
threads to be
found but also it's got teeth um and
as i once told the students and
immediately regretted it i was teaching
in high school
uh that it has bones of crystallized
tragedy
um which i think was a bit much for her
um you know so so i think about the
the wrestling piece um
so this is what i'm thinking sorry i'm
kind of a little all over the place
there's a certain kind of thing that
happens often in these kinds of
conversations which is like there's kind
of a weaving and a certain amount of
something there's like backup and spark
and weaving right
and it's very different than state
debate
where you have the the confrontational
aspect right
and uh when you do have debates i was
watching the
fragments of the us debate and it's not
clear that debates mean what they used
to
but um you know i sometimes wonder about
what the
what the sort of exchanges between those
things like is it is a weave and a flow
can that get you everywhere do you have
to do you think have wrestling
does there need to be conflict like how
do those things fit together
and yes yeah i mean i think so
you know at the same time i'm i'm very
interested in like the anti-debate
as a concept right which is like uh
rather than just trying to like get your
opponent with points
you form you know steel man versions of
what they're saying and the idea is
really to to create a collaborative
effort and i think sometimes obviously
our adversarial process
loses sight of that um
yeah my intuition here
is that um you don't need classic
debates
anymore but what i do think is required
is
do you have the courage
and the clarity to feel inside of you
that when something is said do you
genuinely
have where you currently are a different
viewpoint
can you articulate it clearly with the
intention
of co-creating greater clarity
with the people that you are with and so
like the way that i imagine it is like
if we're co-weaving a fabric
but my genius and me truly sees like
that's the wrong pattern there
can we deconstruct it can we talk about
why
it's felt that it doesn't fit what was
unfolding
and then can we co-weave together but
it's why i love podcasts and it's
like podcasts have transformed the way
that i speak to people
and the way that i speak to everybody
now is i'm genuinely trying to
feel what is the what is the cloth
the weaving that they are presenting me
is there anything that i genuinely
feel i can learn from their cloth as
it's being presented to add to my cloth
and then is there anything that i
genuinely feel i can add to their cloth
to help move towards the felt sense of
where i
feel they're trying to make their cloth
go
because there is this intuition in me
you know it's the idea of the
damon or the daimon depending on who you
here pronounce it but
that in the same way that every acorn
knows what it's trying to become every
human
on an unconscious level knows what it's
trying to become
and when you're in a conversation can
you feel into what they're becoming is
can you feel what you're becoming is and
then can you trust the fact that
something has brought the two of you
together and then can you be humble
enough to
recognize there is something in this
being that if i was
open and i listened would fundamentally
help me towards whatever my becoming is
and then me offering my truth as i see
it now as i feel it now
can help them in their becoming but the
whole idea of a debate
implies you already know and so you
learn nothing
yeah i mean i think eric you put that so
beautifully i i don't think i have
much to add to it other than um when i
mentioned
you anderson i think yes i wasn't saying
yet we should just have debate it's it's
more it's more akin to
the manner of um it's it's it's our
intention towards the whole of the
process both before and after so how do
we catch each other
how do we hold each other how do we
share with each other after the
confrontation
you know as well as before i see these
things as kind of like a dynamic
relationship between confrontation and
surrender
and there are appropriate and
inappropriate kinds of both
right so it's inappropriate for me to
confront if for example
i like the way you put it eric if i if i
don't have the intention to bring sort
of greater clarity or otherwise sort of
um
develop or raise the space that we're
all inhabiting in some sense to make
a deep contribution to what is integris
about
the fabric that is we're co-weaving
together which
at the same time is in some sense our
very coherence and
being in the world together um and then
the surrender piece
is like well sometimes you know it's
it's like um
it's to to simply appreciate and be
moved by the flow of another and then
sometimes uh
you you need to stop being moved by that
flow because they're spiraling you off
into some sort of titrated oblivion with
just boxes and boxes and it's repressing
that creative spirit and so actually
it's not it's not the right way
yeah i think a lot of it i mean it's
interesting
that obviously there's an intuitive
component right to sort of feeling your
way through
right and getting a sense of where
you're lining up with people and what
they have to
offer and what you know how how you sort
of plug together in some sense
um but there's also there's an element
of
like flexibility that's required right
people all together too often want to
play
one role um i used to have a friend
who um
any time we were doing something social
he always wanted to be the straight man
so i had to play the fool and this was
this was the dynamic that he
preferred right um it was a was it that
we were business partners
and so it was this thing that we did um
and it was fine i i enjoy playing the
fool sometimes and
um he liked looking like that uh grumpy
eagle from the muppets
and like that it was a social thing that
we did right
but it did sometimes strike me at the
time and it's like oh my god can we
change this up
just like once or twice you know can we
and and i sometimes felt that lack of
flexibility
likewise many years ago uh
a a girlfriend of mine who was
exceptionally clever about this sort of
thing
um had pointed out to me that i very
often would launch into
uh arguments and she's like and i don't
even think you believe what you
are saying you just say a contrary thing
and
i uh was like i certainly don't
um and uh anyway so what she did
she was smart she led me into this trap
basically
she started arguing a point it must have
been pre-planned but she started arguing
this point
and i of course took up the counterpoint
and then moved by move
she gradually shifted the nature of her
argument and her position
until she was arguing the opposite right
at which point i
in perfect lockstep had switched to
arguing her original point
and then she was like see yes this is
what i'm talking about
and and i suddenly was like oh
i am and like why am i doing that and
i i had a real deep moment of access and
i was like why am i doing that
i'm doing it because it's counterpoint
i'm doing it to play the devil's
advocate because my sense is that that's
how one fills
out right not necessarily but it was
really
it was a revelation for me at the time
at 16 or something
because it was like right a a dance is
not just
you know taking up the opposite position
with somebody and then following them
move for move
there's something that is more
improvisational and there's something
that requires a kind of a fluidity
um a shift so that you can first do one
thing and then do
another um and i think the same goes
with this kind of like the contact of
the fabric right sometimes
things have to shift around right
um a little bit just to to kind of
i don't know catalyze the effect of
something
i love that point and the thing that
comes up in me and this is something
that i
constantly say to my friends who i can
feel
um this is something that i constantly
say to my friends who
whatever is being proposed by the
mainstream
they must believe the opposite and it's
that
the rebel is enslaved in the same way
that the slave is because the rebel
doesn't know their true point the rebel
has to be the opposite of whatever the
thing is that's being offered
and that that seems like a transitionary
stage to your authentic self
but if you've got a lot of people
especially people who are very low in
agreeableness they just stay there
and um i find that
whenever i'm talking to someone who is
like
that uh i find myself
becoming the advocate trying to steal
man that i don't believe
you know that's coming through the
mainstream just to give them the sense
of like
do you see how you are not free
because no matter what is presented you
have to not believe it
and you think that that's you being the
divine arbiter
you know like the revolutionary like the
difference between the rebel and the
revolutionary
is that the rebel is enslaved to be the
opposite of whatever tradition is
but the revolutionary on some sense i
think in its highest aspect
is like a prophet that it has something
genuine and unique coming through it
that it's the advocate
for yeah that's right i mean the prophet
doesn't just
you know obviously there's like a
tradition a prophetic tradition
that has the the wild man wander out of
the desert you know with
long beard and a mouthful of bees and
honey um
you know and and say like this is all
screwed up and we should stop it
right um but usually that
that comes with some kind of like
actually
proactive you know prescriptive
vision of what what needs to happen um
and i think yeah all together too often
people um
especially because it's been so
valorized in the west
right the idea of rebel consciousness is
so
um valorized and and you know and i
think that there's something to it right
that there was never a change of any
kind
that wasn't first an unpopular
rebellious position right and
i think i probably said for 25 years uh
the minority
isn't always right but the majority is
always wrong
i love it i don't i'm not so sure it's
true
in quite the same way i mean that that
kept me from doing things like um
i didn't wear shoes for years
and you know i had other things combat
boots and stuff but like
i didn't wear shoes i didn't wear um
shorts
shorts were like this shockingly like i
wore them as a child
and then as soon as i was able to make
my own determinations i didn't wear
shorts
and i looked back on that period and i'm
like why did i have that strange
position you know what are great
shorts and
it's a majority position like there was
really a common wisdom about keeping
your legs reasonably cool in the summer
so you know i i don't hold it quite as
strongly but by the same token
you know that that idea that the
minority isn't always right but the
majority is always wrong
does carry in a certain sense because
you know as i sometimes say to my
clients it's like
well it's not that way because if it was
if the majority was right then the world
would be a very different place wouldn't
it
like and the proof of the pudding is in
the eating you know like this is
this is what we got and this is what we
got from what most people believe
so should we continue to believe that
maybe not yeah i think what i i think
part of what i heard there was this
relationship between
the wisdom of crowds and also the
madness of crowds
and i think what's most important is the
capacity to discern
in whatever the case is in fact the
wisdom
and that there's something else that's
really coming coming through to me here
when we speak about
vision um and fabric
and it's the notion of religion it's a
notion of something we can
all gather around in some sense even if
we want to
understand that center as a wandering
center as a moving center could to
continually be
re-realized and re-woven still some
inner orientation towards something that
together we can
share in
thank you for listening and if you enjoy
these podcasts please consider sharing
them or leaving a review
and perhaps also to consider supporting
it on patreon.com
voicecraft your support makes a
life-changing difference and a
life-affirming impact
it will help sustain the podcast build
the network and make possible more
community events and educational
resources
read about member benefits at
patreon.com
voicecraft there are breadcrumbs to
follow if you look